A Guide to the Viola O. Baskerville Papers, 1961-2005 (bulk 1994-2005)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Viola O. Baskerville Papers, 1961-2005 (bulk 1994-2005)
The Library of Virginia
42532
1.35 cu. ft.
Viola O. Baskerville
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Viola O. Baskerville, 2006 January
Biographical Information
Viola Osborne Baskerville was born on 29 October 1951 in Richmond, Virginia. She graduated form the College of William and Mary in 1973 with a B.A. in German Literature and received a Fulbright Scholarship to attend the University of Bonn in Germany the same year. In 1979, Baskerville earned a J.D. from the University of Iowa, College of Law. In 1994 she was elected to the Richmond City Council and served until her election to the Virginia House of Delegates in 1998. In 2005 Baskerville stepped down from her Delegate position to run for the Democratic nomination for Lieutenant Governor, but was unsuccessful in her bid. In December 2005 Baskerville was picked by incoming Virginia Governor, Tim Kaine to be Secretary of Administration.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1961-2005, of Viola O. Baskerville including campaign material, clippings, correspondence, House Bills, House Joint Resolutions, photographs, and speeches. Of note are several House Bills sponsored by Baskerville including emergency contraception legislation, Mayor at large legislation for the City of Richmond, and obesity, health and physical education in the public schools. Also of note is Joint Resolution 613 announcing the General Assembly's profound regret over the 1959-1964 closing of the public schools in Prince Edward County.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series 1. House of Delegate Files, 1961-2005
Series 2. Media Clippings, 1989-2005
Contents List
- House of Delegates Files, 1961-2005., Extent: 2 boxes. (Box 1-2)
  This series consists of various House Bills sponsored by Baskerville, background material related to House Bill, and House Joint Resolutions. Also included are subject files related to sponsored bills.
  Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - Announcement to Run for Lt. Governor/Endorsements, 2001-2005. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Black History Month, undated. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Budget Amendments, 2005. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - House Bill 162 -- Unemployment Compensation Follow the Spouse, 1998. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - House Bill 176 -- Mayor at Large Legislation for the City of Richmond, 2004-2005. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - House Bill 220 -- Prostitution; While Infected with HIV, 1997-1998. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - House Bill 846 -- The Brown v. Board of Education Scholarship Program and Fund, 2004. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - House Bill 846 -- The Brown v. Board of Education Scholarship Program and Fund, 2003-2004. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - House Bill 846 -- Background, 2004. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - House Bill 1257 -- Day-Care Facility Investment Tax Credit, 1998. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - House Bill 1258 -- Carrying Loaded Firearms in Public Areas, 1998. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - House Bill 1259 -- Medicaid; Family Planning, 1990-1998. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - House Bill 1605 -- Use of Flashing Amber Lights by Neighborhood Watch Patrol Vehicles, 2005. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - House Bill 1900 -- Civil Immunity for Employers Providing On-site Child Care, 2005. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - House Bill 1901 -- Background, 2005. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - House Bill 1902 -- Virginia Caregivers Grant Program, 2005. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - House Bill 1902 -- Background, 2005. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - House Bill 1903 -- Medical Mapractice Claims and Reporting, 2005. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - House Bill 1903 -- Background, 2005. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - House Bill 1904 -- Medical Malpractice: Expressions Inadmissible, 2005. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - House Bill 1904 -- Background, 2004. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - House Bill 1905 -- Clean Election Act and Fund, 2005. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - House Bill 1905 -- Background, 2005. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - House Bill 1906 -- Alternative Education Programs; Change in Provisions of Standard of Quality, 1998-2005. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - House Bill 1909 -- Absentee Ballots, 2005. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - House Bill 1909 -- Background, undated. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - House Bill 2568 -- Educational Benefits for Dependents of Members of the Military, 2004-2005. (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - House Bill 2569 -- Background, 2004-2005. (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - House Bill 2610 -- Obesity, and Health and Physical Education in the Public Schools, 2005. (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - House Bill 2610 -- Background, 2005. (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - House Bill 2718 -- Sexual Orientation, undated. (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - House Bill 2733 -- Membership and Duties of the Small Business Commission, 2004-2005. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - House Bill 2733 -- Background, 2004-2005. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - House Bill 2782 -- Emergency Contraception Access Initiative, 2000-2001. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - House Bill 2796 -- Background, 2004-2005. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - House Bill 2845 -- Background, 2002-2005. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - House Joint Resolution -- To Study the Various Alternative Uses for Existing Historic State Buildings in the Downtown Richmond Area, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - House Joint Resolution 613 -- General Assembly's Profound Regret Over the 1959-1964 Closing of the Public Schools in Prince Edward County, 2001-2004. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - House Joint Resolution 613 -- Background, 1961-2003. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - House Joint Resolution 617 -- Requesting Virginia Housing Development Authority to Study the Availability of Affordable Housing for Active Military Personnel and their Families Living in Virginia, 2004-2005. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - House Joint Resolution 705 -- Background, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - House Joint Resolution 792 -- Urging the FDA to Approve Over-the-counter Status for Emergency Contraception, 2001. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - House of Delegates First Campaign, 1994-1998. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1999-2005. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Legislation, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Military Family Support, 2004-2005. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Resume/Biography, undated. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Small, Women, Minority Business, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Women's Health, 1999-2002. (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Media Clippings, 1989-2005., Extent: 1 box. (Box 3)
  The series consist mainly of newspaper clipping, speeches, correspondence, campaign materials, and photographs.
  Arranged chronologically by year.
  - Gubernatorial Board Appointment -- Newspaper Articles and Letters from Govenors, 1989-1993. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Media Clippings Miscellaneous, 1993-1997. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Media Clippings, 1994. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Media Clippings -- Campaign for City Council, 1994-1995. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Media Clippings, 1995. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Media Clippings, 1996. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Media Clippings, 1996. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Media Clippings, 1997-1999. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Media Clippings, 1997. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Media Clippings, 1998. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Media Clippings, 1999. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Legislative Media Clippings, 2001. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Legislative Media Clippings, 2002. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Legislative Media Clippings, 2003. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Legislative Media Clippings, 2004. (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Legislative Media Clippings, 2005. (Box 3, Folder 16)